<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<help>

 <title>leafDrums 2.3 help</title>
 <prefix>leafDrums 2.3: </prefix>

 <copycontent>
  <file><name>style.css</name><target></target></file>
  <file><name>seealso.gif</name><target></target></file>
 </copycontent>

 <section id="tutorial" showdepth="0">
  <title>Tutorial</title>

  <summary>
   <p>
    If you're new to leafDrums, you should begin by going through this tutorial,
	which takes around ten minutes and will ensure you have a good basic understanding
	of the program.
   </p>
  </summary>

  <content>
   <p>
    The tutorial takes about ten minutes. Begin by clicking on 'Introduction'.
   </p>
  </content>

  <page id="introduction">
   <title>Introduction</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 This tutorial introduces you to leafDrums. If you work through it in order
	 (switching between this tutorial and the program) you will have a good grasp of
	 the basic concepts you need to understand, and you'll have created a basic
	 drum rhythm.
	</p>

	<p>
	 It should take between five and fifteen minutes (depending on how fast you read
	 and work) to complete the tutorial.
	</p>

	<p>
	 The last page of the tutorial has helpful tips to point you in the right direction
	 when you want to achieve more advanced results - so even if you think you don't
	 need to work through the whole tutorial, it's worth checking that out.
	</p>

	<p class="sidetrack">
	 One last thing before we start; when you see text like this, it is a sidetrack.
	 You don't need to read the text or follow the link to complete the tutorial.
	</p>

    <p>
	 Now let's begin the tutorial by taking a look at the leafDrums song screen,
	 which is what you see when the program starts.
	</p>
   </content>
  </page>

  <page id="songscreen">
   <title>The song screen</title>

   <content>
    <p>
     leafDrums begins with the song screen. This screen shows the song
     (which is a collection of patterns), the drums used in the song,
     and one of the patterns in the song.
    </p>

	<p>
	 <image file="songscreen.gif" alt="The song screen"/>
	</p>

	<p class="sidetrack">
	 <link id="../reference/songscreen">More information about the song screen...</link>
	</p>

	<p>
	 Notice the 'mouse icons' in various parts of the screen? They describe
	 what will happen if you click the mouse in that area, and any keys
	 (Shift, Ctrl) that might modify that behaviour. This information is there
	 on-screen so that you don't have to constantly refer back to the on-line
	 help in normal use.
	</p>

	<terminology>
	 <term>Song</term>
	 <definition>
	  <em>Songs</em> are what you create in leafDrums. The song contains patterns,
	  drum sounds, and so on. The song controls which patterns are played in each
	  bar.
	 </definition>
	</terminology>

	<terminology>
	 <term>Pattern</term>
	 <definition>
	  A <em>pattern</em> contains some drum hits. (For example, you might make a
	  pattern that contained four kick drum hits, one on each beat.) Patterns
	  are always one bar long. You place a pattern into a specific bar
	  of the song (or more than one bar) so that it will be played as part of
	  the song.
	 </definition>
	</terminology>

    <p>
	 In order to create the song, you place drum hits into patterns. You
	 then place the patterns into bars of the song. If you want the same pattern
	 to play multiple times, you place it into multiple bars.
	</p>

	<p>
	 Next, we'll begin to do just that.
	</p>
   </content>
  </page>

  <page id="gettingstarted">
   <title>Getting started</title>

   <content>

    <p>
	 Let's begin creating a simple rhythm. Along the way, you'll see most of
	 the basic features leafDrums has to offer.
	</p>

	<subhead>Naming patterns</subhead>

	<p>
	 First we'll rename the existing pattern, which is currently (and
	 rather unimaginatively) titled '1'. Renaming patterns doesn't make any difference
	 as far as the system is concerned, but it can make the rhythm a lot clearer
	 to you. It's good practice to give each pattern a reasonably meaningful name
	 (as far as possible in the small space available).
	</p>

	<p class="do">
	 Click on the 'Rename' button in the pattern display. Then type a short name
	 for the pattern, such as 'main', and press the Enter key.
	</p>
	<p class="result">
	 <image file="renamed.gif" alt="Renamed pattern"/>
	</p>

	<subhead>Placing patterns into song</subhead>

	<p>
   leafDrums begins with a single copy of this pattern in the first (and, so
	 far, only) bar of the song.
	</p>
  <p>
    <image file="initialpattern.gif" alt="Initial pattern"/>
  </p>
  <p>
    If you create other patterns, or want more than one copy of the same
    pattern, you will need to add those to the song yourself.
  </p>
  <p>
    Let's suppose we want to add a second copy of the pattern in the song,
    so that it plays twice.
  </p>

	<p class="do">
	 Click in the song display, in the blank area just beneath the number 2 and
   to the right of the second orange line.
	</p>
	<p class="result">
    <image file="secondpattern.gif" alt="After placing second pattern"/>
	</p>

	<p>
	  The 'main' pattern is now included in the second bar of the song.
	  Note that one other thing happened: an extra blank space has been added
    to the right (in the location for the third bar).
	</p>

	<p>
    The blank space in bar three is so you can place another pattern there.
    leafDrums always gives you one space beyond the length of the song, so that
    you can extend the song. (If you actually want a blank space in your song,
    you'll have to first put a pattern there, then add a pattern in the following bar
    as well, and finally remove the first pattern by clicking on it again.)
  </p>

  <subhead>L and R markers</subhead>

  <p>
    The orange L and R markers indicate the area of song you are working on.
    When you click Play, the song will play from the L marker up to the R marker.
  </p>
  <p>
    Notice that the L and R markers currently include only the first bar. You
    need to move the R marker to after the second bar.
  </p>

  <p class="do">
    Move the mouse pointer over the vertical dotted line just to the right of
    bar two. You should notice the help text below the song change to indicate
    that the mouse buttons now have different behaviour. Click the right mouse
    button to set the R marker.
  </p>
  <p class="result">
    <image file="rmarker.gif" alt="After moving R marker"/>
  </p>

  <subhead>Tracks</subhead>

	<p>
    You may be wondering why there is a blank row underneath the patterns you
    placed. This is a second <em>track</em>. If you place patterns in the
    second track, leafDrums will give you a blank third track to use, and so on.
	</p>

	<terminology>
	 <term>Track</term>
	 <definition>
	  Each song can contain one or more <em>tracks</em>. Each bar of the track can
	  have a single pattern assigned to it, or it can be blank. All the tracks
    play at once, so when you want to play more than one pattern at a time, you
    place the multiple patterns across several tracks.
    Tracks have independent level controls.
	 </definition>
	</terminology>

  <subhead>Moving on...</subhead>
  <p>
    We've created a song which includes the same pattern twice, and set that
    song so that both patterns will be played back. However,
    our pattern doesn't contain any drum hits yet, so it will be silent.
	  Next, we'll place some hits.
	</p>
   </content>
  </page>

  <page id="firstplay">
   <title>Let's make some noise</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 In this page of the tutorial, we're going to complete a very simple rhythm, and
	 hear it play.
	</p>

	<subhead>The pattern display</subhead>

	<p>
	 <image file="patterndisplay.gif" alt="The pattern display"/>
	</p>

	<p class="sidetrack">
	 <link id="../reference/patterndisplay">More information about the pattern display...</link>
	</p>

	<p>
	 The pattern display shows where you have placed drum hits in the current pattern.
	 Hits are marked with circles; thin circles for normal hits, thick circles for
	 accented hits. They are shown on the grid, which indicates beats and quarter beats
	 by different strength of line.
	</p>

	<subhead>Adding drum hits</subhead>

	<p class="do">
	 Add some drum hits in the first <em>line</em> of the pattern. For example,
	 you might want to add one hit on each beat. To add a hit, simply click
	 where you would like to place it.
	</p>
	<p class="result">
	 <image file="addedhits.gif" alt="The added hits"/>
	</p>

	<terminology>
	 <term>Line</term>
	 <definition>
	  A song contains <em>lines</em>. Each line corresponds to one drum sound
	  that is included in the song. The lines are displayed on the song screen,
	  stretching across the drums display (which shows the drum sound, level,
	  and left-right panning that are associated with that line) and the
	  pattern display (which shows the drum hits on that line in the current
	  pattern).
	 </definition>
	</terminology>

	<p>
	 As before, once you have used a line, leafDrums adds another one below it
	 so that you can place hits for another drum sound.
	</p>

	<p>
	 You've now added some drum hits. And this pattern is included in the first
	 bar of the song, so when you play the song you should hear those hits right
	 away. Only one small problem - you haven't chosen a drum sound for the hits.
	</p>

	<subhead>The drum screen</subhead>

	<p class="do">
	 Click on the 'Click to set...' button in the drums display. (There are two
	 'Click to set...' buttons; click the upper one, since it corresponds to the
	 line you placed hits on.)
	</p>

	<image file="drumscreen.gif" alt="The drum screen"/>

	<p class="sidetrack">
	 <link id="../reference/drumscreen">More information about the drum screen...</link>
	</p>

	<p>
	 The drum screen contains two sections; a list of available sounds, and an
	 audio processing section. leafDrums has a decent set of fun audio processing
	 features, but we won't be covering those in the tutorial; when you <em>do</em>
	 want to know about audio processing, there is a reference topic about the
	 <link id="../reference/audiodisplay">audio processing display</link>.
	</p>

	<subhead>Selecting a sound</subhead>

	<p class="do">
	 Click on a drum sound from the list on the left.
	</p>
	<p class="result">
	 <image file="selecteddrum.gif" alt="A selected drum sound"/>
	</p>

	<p>
	 You've now selected a drum sound for this line of the song and therefore the
	 pattern.
	</p>

	<p>
	 Before we play the song, this is a good moment to explain how the sounds list
	 works.
	</p>

	<subhead>The sounds list</subhead>

	<p>
	 The list displays every .wav and .ogg sound file within a certain folder or
	 folders on your hard disk. (By default, this is the 'Sounds' sub-folder
	 underneath the folder where you installed leafDrums.)
	</p>

	<p>
	 Files that are within sub-folders of that folder are included too. You
	 can see here that there are several folders: the 'Drums' folder contains
	 the 'Cymbals' and 'Kicks' folder, and a few others. If you want to hide
	 or show drums within a certain folder, click its title (this is useful
	 when you have more drums).
	</p>

	<p>
	 leafDrums comes with a very limited selection of drum sounds so you will
	 definitely want to obtain more, perhaps by downloading them from the
	 Internet or sampling them yourself. In addition, when you create tracks
	 in leafDrums you might also want custom sounds such as vocals; you might
	 even want to include short melodic passages or bass lines so that you can put
	 together an entire track in leafDrums. (leafDrums is not really designed
	 for this, however, and you can't incorporate very long samples such as
	 vocals for an entire track.)
	</p>

	<p>
	 When you want to add a sound file so that leafDrums can use it, the
	 easiest way is to click the 'Open' button next to the little folder icon 
	 (<em>not</em> the big Open button at the top of the screen).
	 This opens a standard view on to the folder where drums are stored. You
	 can then drag your own sounds into that folder or its subfolders, or
	 create new subfolders. Once you're done, go back to leafDrums and click
	 the 'Refresh' button, and you'll see the new sounds.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	 leafDrums supports all .wav formats that your computer can read. It also
	 supports compressed .ogg files. (It does not support MP3s.)
	</p>

	<subhead>Playing the song!</subhead>

	<p class="do">
	 Anyway, you've created a very simple rhythm. Play it by clicking on the
	 'Play' button at the top left.
	</p>

	<p>
	 You should hear the rhythm. If you like, you can change the drum sound
	 now, by clicking another sound. You can do this even while the song is
   playing - everything in leafDrums can be changed during playback, although
   it might take a second to react.
	</p>

	<p>
	 When you get fed up of it, notice that the 'Play' button has turned into
	 'Stop'. Click the button again to stop the rhythm.
	</p>

	<subhead>Returning to the song screen</subhead>

	<p>
	 You probably want to return to the song screen so that you can adjust
	 the levels and add more drums to the rhythm.
	</p>

	<p>
	 There are two ways to get back to the song screen:
	</p>

	<ul>
	 <li>Click either one of the 'Song' buttons at the bottom of the screen.</li>
	 <li>Press the F5 key.</li>
	</ul>

	<p>
	 If you use the program a lot, you'll get used to that shortcut. (Note that
	 F6 works the other way, to take you to the drum screen when you're on
	 the song screen. There are other <link id="../reference/keyboard">keyboard
   shortcuts</link> that you might want to learn.)
	</p>

	<p>
	 In any case, you should now be back at the song screen, and ready to
	 add more sounds to your rhythm.
	</p>

	<p>
	 This is the end of the step-by-step tutorial, but the next page includes
	 some useful information that should help you get going with more advanced
	 rhythms.
	</p>
   </content>
  </page>

  <page id="fromhere">
   <title>Where to go from here</title>

   <content>

    <p>
	 You've now seen how to create a very simple rhythm in leafDrums. Here are some
	 tips to help you get the best out of the program from now on.
	</p>

	<p>
	 The first thing you should remember is that you can always access this help file
	 (by clicking the Help button). Every control on the screen is explained in the
	 <link id="../reference/">reference</link> section, and the
	 <link id="../advanced/">advanced</link> section contains useful advice when you're
	 looking to take things that bit further. Whenever you're a bit confused about
	 something or not quite sure how it is supposed to work, <em>do</em> check the
	 help file.
	</p>

	<p>
	 Apart from that...
	</p>

	<subhead>Top tips</subhead>

	<ul>
	 <li><em>Get more drum sounds.</em><br/>
	     The drums provided with leafDrums are very basic indeed. Although you
		 can get some quite varied sounds if you apply creative
		 <link id="../reference/audiodisplay">effects</link>, they still aren't
		 sufficient for real use; they're intended only so that you can get
		 started with the program right away.<br/>But the good news is that there are
		 many places where you can download drum sounds as .wav files online;
		 some of these are linked from the
		 <link url="http://www.leafdigital.com/software/leafdrums/">leafDrums web
		 page</link>.</li>

     <li><em>Make your own sounds.</em><br/>
	     Don't forget that you can sample your own sounds too (by recording them as
		 standard CD-quality .wav files). You could
		 record your favourite drum machine; record live drums; or sample beats and
		 loops from CDs that you like.</li>

	 <li><em>Avoid repeating yourself.</em><br/>
	     leafDrums can play more than one pattern at a time, if you use different
		 tracks. Use this facility to place common parts of your rhythm into
		 different patterns; this will save you having to re-do the same hi-hat
		 sequence in different patterns.</li>

	 <li><em>Use accurate timing for more interesting rhythms.</em><br/>
	     Rather than positioning every drum on a beat or quarter beat, remember
		 to turn on 'fine grid' occasionally so that you can get the timing just
		 right. You might also want to use triplets sometimes.<br/>
		 <link id="../reference/patterndisplay">(More information on the
		 pattern display...)</link></li>

	 <li><em>Use repeats.</em><br/>
	     If you create a long repetitive song, you can save a lot of time by
		 using arrows and flags on the song display to make some sections of
		 the song repeat.<br/>
		 <link id="../reference/songdisplay">(More information on the
		 song display...)</link></li>

	 <li><em>Join the mailing list or forum.</em><br/>
	     If you use leafDrums seriously, you should consider joining the
		 <link id="../program/community">mailing list or Web forum</link>, 
		 where you can discuss the program with other users and perhaps 
		 learn useful skills from them.</li>
	</ul>

	<p>
	 Well, that's all for now. I hope you find the program easy to use and fun.
	 If you <em>do</em> like it, please consider <link id="../program/ordering">registering
	 (paying for) the
	 program</link>.
	</p>

   </content>
  </page>
 </section>

 <section id="reference" showdepth="1">
  <title>Reference</title>

  <summary>
   <p>
    The reference section contains information on every section of the
  	two main screens of the program.
   </p>
  </summary>

  <content>
   <p>
    This section contains information on every part of the two main screens.
	  Select the screen you want more information about, then select a more
	  precise item from the list within the screen page.
   </p>
   <p>
    There is also a list of keyboard controls.
   </p>
  </content>

  <page id="songscreen">
   <title>Song screen</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 <image file="songscreen.gif" alt="Song screen"/>
	</p>

    <p>
	 This screen contains four sections:
	</p>

	<ul>
	 <li>The <em>control bar</em> (green background)<br/>
	     Contains a Play button, a master level control, an output
		 level and clipping indicator, and other buttons to perform
		 standard tasks<br/>
		 <link id="controlbar">More info...</link></li>
	 <li>The <em>song display</em> (red-brown background)<br/>
	     Shows the way that patterns have been put together to make
		 a leafDrums song. Use this area to place patterns in the song,
		 to change tempo, to adjust levels, etc.<br/>
		 <link id="songdisplay">More info...</link></li>
	 <li>The <em>drums display</em> (yellow-grey background)<br/>
	     Shows the drums that are used by this song. Click on a drum to
		 enter the <link id="drumscreen">drum screen</link> and alter
		 it<br/>
		 <link id="drumsdisplay">More info...</link></li>
	 <li>The <em>pattern display</em> (blue background)<br/>
	     Displays one pattern from the song. Click in the pattern to
		 place drum hits<br/>
		 <link id="patterndisplay">More info...</link></li>
	</ul>
   </content>

   <page id="controlbar">
	<title>Control bar</title>

	<content>
	 <p>
	  The control bar is always available at the top of the leafDrums
	  screen.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  <image file="controlbar.gif" alt="The control bar"/>
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Play/Stop</subhead>
	 <p>
	  The left-hand button begins playing the drum pattern. When the
	  pattern is playing, the same button becomes 'Stop', and you can
	  click to stop it.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  The pattern is played from the L marker (in the
	  <link id="songdisplay">song display</link>) to the R marker.
	  Once the R marker is reached, playback will either stop,
    or (if 'Loop' is selected in the song display) loop back to the L
	  marker and continue.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can see the current play position on the song display. When
	  play reaches the end of the song display, the display
	  automatically scrolls so that you can see the area being played.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Instead of clicking the button, you can also play or stop the song
	  using the space bar.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  If you get errors when you click Play, or if playing does not
	  seem to work properly, make sure that you have DirectX installed.
	  leafDrums should work with any version of DirectX, but has only
	  been tested with DirectX 8. (You can check which version you
	  have installed by clicking Start, Run and typing 'dxdiag'. If
	  that command gives an error, or if the version number it reports
	  is less than 8, you should install DirectX 8 from
	  <link url="http://www.microsoft.com/directx/">http://www.microsoft.com/directx/</link>.)
	 </p>


	 <subhead>Level slider</subhead>
	 <p>
	  This slider is the master level control for the song. Move it right
	  or left to make the song louder or quieter.
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  It is a digital level control (in other words, it is not simply
	  connected to the 'Wave' output level in the sound card mixer),
	  so it does affect the sound quality. For optimum quality, you
	  should set the level control to the maximum which does not
	  result in clipping of the sound (see below).
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Output level display</subhead>
	 <p>
	  This display shows the current output sound level, while the
	  song is playing.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If the output <em>clips</em>, a red section at the right of the
	  level display will remain lit for a while. This indicates that
	  you should reduce the level slider.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  The level display is not always perfectly synchronized with the
	  actual sound. (leafDrums calculates the output audio some way
	  ahead of actual playback, so it's not always easy to work out
	  which level should be displayed.)
	 </p>

	 <subhead>New</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Click New to create a new song. Any existing song
	  is cleared (you will be prompted to save it if it was changed),
	  and a new blank song is created.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Open</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Click Open when you want to open a song you created before.
	  You can only open files that were created with leafDrums 2.0+,
	  not files that were created with older versions of this software
	  or with any other program.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  The Open button is not used to load .wav files into your drum rhythm.
	  Please see the <link id="drumscreen">drum screen reference</link>
	  for more information on that.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Save</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Click Save to save the current song. You will be prompted for
	  a filename for the song.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  In the Save dialog, you can choose whether to embed audio
	  data.
	 </p>
	 <ul>
	  <li>
	   If you embed audio data, all the sounds needed to play
	   the song are included in the song file. You should use this
	   option if you need to send a file to somebody else who might
	   not have all the drum sounds that you do. This can result in
	   large files.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	   If you do not embed audio data, sounds are not included in
	   the song file, and you will need to have the same sound files
	   available when you want to open the song again. (Sounds
	   are still embedded if you do not have them on your system, in
	   other words if you previously opened a file with embedded
	   sounds.)
	  </li>
	 </ul>
	 <p>
	  You can also save the song by pressing Ctrl+S. This saves the
	  song under the same filename it already has, and does not
	  embed audio data.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  leafDrums autosaves every five minutes (if the file has changed
	  since last save). If the program crashes when you had unsaved work, 
	  the autosaved version will automatically be opened next time you
	  start leafDrums.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Write</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Click Write to write the current song (between L and R markers)
	  into an audio file. You can choose three file formats:
	 </p>
	 <ul>
	  <li>44.1 kHz 16-bit stereo .wav.<br/>
	      No quality loss. Appropriate for loading into other music software.</li>
	  <li>High quality .ogg.<br/>
	      High-quality compressed audio. Appropriate for files you want to share
	      across the Internet where quality is important, such as drum loops you
	      are providing for other musicians.</li>
	  <li>Web quality .ogg.<br/>
	      Lower quality compressed audio (equivalent to 128 kb/s MP3). Appropriate
	      when quality is not the prime concern, such as if providing a version of
	      a composition for Web page visitors.</li>
	 </ul>
	 <p>
	  You will be prompted to select the number of copies you want
	  (for example, if you have made a two-bar loop and you would like
	  the saved file to contain four copies of this loop). Then
	  you can enter a name for the file.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you want to write the entire song, make sure to set the L and
	  R markers appropriately before you click Write.
	 </p>
   <p>
     You can write the song into more than one file (so that either
     each drum sound is in a different file, or each track is in a different file),
     which may be useful if you have multi-track recording software.
   </p>

	 <subhead>Help</subhead>
	 <p>
	  You will be shocked to discover that the Help button brings up this help file.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Quit</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Click Quit to exit the program. If you have made changes to the
	  song, you will be given the chance to save it.
	 </p>
	</content>
   </page>

   <page id="songdisplay">
	<title>Song display</title>

	<content>
	 <p>
	  The song display shows which patterns have been placed into tracks
	  of the song, and allows you to change this. It also includes general
	  song options.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  <image file="songdisplay.gif" alt="The song display"/>
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Main display</subhead>
	 <p>
	  The main display shows each track of the song and the patterns that
	  have been placed onto those tracks. Each bar of the song is numbered
	  so that you can tell where you are if you're scrolling through a long
	  song.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Handling patterns in the song</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  You can place a pattern onto a particular bar of a track by clicking
	  in that space; that will add a copy of the current pattern (the one
	  that is selected in the <link id="patterndisplay">pattern display</link>)
	  at that point.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Clicking in an occupied space will remove the pattern from that space.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you right-click on a pattern, that pattern will become the current
	  pattern and will be shown in the pattern display.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you hold down Ctrl and click a blank space, this will create a new
	  pattern and place it into the location where you clicked. (This can be
	  more convenient than using the New button in the pattern display, since
	  it places the pattern at the same time as creating it.)
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  When you place a pattern in the last bar of the song, an extra blank
	  bar is added for you. (This bar isn't considered as fully part of the
	  song until you place something into it.)
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you create more bars than will fit on the screen, you can use the
	  horizontal scrollbar to move around the song.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Handling tracks</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Each line of the song display represents one track. A track can have a
	  single pattern at each bar. There are multiple tracks so that you can
	  play multiple patterns at the same time.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  When you use the last, blank track (by placing a pattern in it),
	  leafDrums automatically creates another track below, in case you need
	  to use another one. Don't worry if you don't need to use it; blank
	  tracks don't use processor time when playing.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can adjust the level for a track using the level slider by that
	  track.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you use more than four tracks, you can use the vertical scrollbar
	  to move between them.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  There is no limit on the number of tracks, but
	  if you use very many tracks which all play sounds at once, you may
	  find that leafDrums cannot keep up when playing the song. If you
	  are likely to test the limits, you should check out the topic on
	  <link id="../advanced/performance">performance</link>.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>L and R markers</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  The orange L and R markers indicate which part of the song will be
	  played when you click Play. This is useful because
	  you can make a small part of the song loop while you are working on
	  it, without having to play the whole song.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can move the markers by clicking with the left (for L) or right
	  (for R) mouse button on the grid lines between bars. The mouse cursor
	  changes when you are in the right place to do this.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Tempo control</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Tempo information is displayed in a narrow line below the tracks. 
	  The tempo in beats per minute is displayed, followed by a time
	  signature such as 4:4.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Bar 1 always contains a tempo setting. Unless you add others, this
	  tempo applies to the entire song.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  To change tempo, scroll so that bar 1 is visible, then click on the 
	  tempo indicator that reads '120 4:4'. A dialog box will appear, allowing
	  you to choose any tempo between 30 and 300 beats per minute, and any number
	  of beats per bar.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Time signatures are always displayed as :4, so if you 
	  actually want	6:8 you will need to choose either 3:4 or 6:4 and set tempo
	  appropriately.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you change the time signature, you need to make sure that patterns match the
	  time signature by adding beats to, or removing beats from, each pattern. 
	  Patterns that don't fit are shown in red in the song display. 
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can add tempo or time signature changes to any bar of the song by clicking
	  in the tempo line underneath that bar. To remove an existing tempo change,
	  right-click on it.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Insert</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Use Insert when you need to add bars to the middle of your song,
	  shifting all the remaining bars along to make room.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Insert operates across all tracks of the song at once, not on a
	  single track.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  To use Insert, click the button and then move the mouse over the
	  song so that the space between two bars is highlighted. This is
	  where your new bar will be inserted.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Click to insert a bar. If you want to insert more than one, hold
	  down Ctrl while you click, and leafDrums will remain in insert mode.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you decide not to insert a bar after all, press Esc to cancel.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Delete</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Use Delete when you need to remove bars from the middle of your song,
	  shifting all the remaining bars along to fill the gap.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Delete operates across all tracks of the song at once, not on a
	  single track. It does not delete the actual patterns (use Delete in
	  the <link id="patterndisplay">pattern display</link> if you want
	  to do that).
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  To use Delete, click the button and then move the mouse over the
	  song so that the bar you want to delete is highlighted.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Click to delete a bar. If you want to delete more than one, hold
	  down Ctrl while you click, and leafDrums will remain in delete mode.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you decide not to delete a bar after all, press Esc to cancel.
	 </p>

   <subhead>Select</subhead>
   <p>
     Using Select, you can make a copy of part of the song in order to paste
     it elsewhere.
   </p>
   <p>
     Click Select, then click and drag around an area in the song (you should
     see the selected area highlighted).
   </p>
	 <p>
	  If you decide not to select anything after all, press Esc to cancel.
	 </p>

   <subhead>Paste</subhead>
   <p>
     Once you have selected an area, click Paste to paste it into the song.
     (Note that this only works within a single copy of leafDrums. You can't
     paste data from any other program, or data selected in a separate copy
     of leafDrums.)
   </p>
   <p>
     After you click Paste, move the mouse over the song. You should see a
     highlighted area where the pasted items will be placed.
   </p>
   <ul>
     <li>Click the <em>left button</em> to paste the area into the song,
       shifting along everything in those bars to make room</li>
     <li>Click the <em>right button</em> to paste on top of what's already in
       those bars, erasing the existing content</li>
     <li>Hold Ctrl while you click if you want to paste more than one copy</li>
   </ul>
	 <p>
	  If you decide not to paste anything after all, press Esc to cancel.
	 </p>

   <subhead>Loop checkbox</subhead>
	 <p>
	  The Loop checkbox controls whether or not the song should be treated
	  as a loop.
	 </p>
	 <p>
 	  This not only affects playback (whether leafDrums loops endlessly when
    you click Play, or stops once it reaches the R marker) but also controls
    the way sounds behave if they would continue after the last bar of the song.
	 </p>
	 <ul>
	  <li>If Loop is selected, then a sound that stretches past the end
		  of the last bar will continue into the first bar</li>
	  <li>If Loop is not selected, then any such sounds will be cut off
		  after the end of the last bar, and not included in the first bar</li>
	 </ul>
	 <p>
	  If you want to try out this difference, try creating a blank song with
	  one bar and then placing a long sound in the last beat. If you turn Loop
	  off and play the song, the song will be silent until that beat. If you
	  have Loop on, you'll hear the latter part of the sound immediately that
	  the song plays.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Level envelope</subhead>
	 <p>
	  When you turn on 'Level envelope', you can create volume level effects
	  (fades) on each track of the song.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You will see a red horizontal line along the top of each track. This
	  line indicates that the track is at 100% volume (relative to its level
	  slider) all the way.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  To create a fade (either in or out):
	 </p>
	 <ul>
	  <li> Click on this red line in two points: where the fade should start,
		   and where the fade should finish</li>
	  <li> You should see two 'nodes' (small black boxes) on the level envelope
		   line, where you clicked</li>
	  <li> Now click and drag the node at the 'fade out' end. Move it to the
		   bottom of the track</li>
	  <li> Play the song; you should hear the fade-in or fade-out that you just
		   created</li>
	 </ul>
	 <p>
	  You can add more nodes by clicking on the red line at other points. If you
	  want to remove nodes, right-click on them.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  When you turn off the 'Level envelope' checkbox, that does not remove the
	  level envelope. It only hides it so that you can edit the pattern more
	  easily without accidentally creating nodes. The envelope is still there and
	  you can turn on 'Level envelope' again when you want to change it.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you really want to get rid of the level envelope, delete each node by
	  right-clicking on it.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Repeats (arrows and flags)</subhead>
	 <p>
	  Sometimes you may need to create a repetitive section of song - for example,
	  you may want to repeat the same four bars eight times. So that you don't
	  have to place the patterns in the song eight times over, you can use <em>arrows</em>
	  and <em>flags</em>.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Flags indicate the beginning of a repeated section, and arrows indicate its end.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can place arrows and flags by moving the mouse over the top of the bar (near the bar
	  number). There are three different colours of arrow and flag; the outer arrow and flag
	  are blue, the middle ones are green, and the inner ones are red. When you create a repeat,
	  you need to use the same colour flag and arrow.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  For example, to make four bars repeat twice in the song, click on the leftmost flag space
	  on the first bar to place a blue flag. Then click on the rightmost arrow space on the final
	  bar of the repeated section to place a blue arrow.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  When you move your mouse over an arrow, you can change the number of times the section is
	  repeated using the right mouse button. Click with the right mouse button to increase the
	  repeat count; hold down Ctrl and click with the right mouse button to decrease it.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you want to <em>nest</em> repeated sections (so that you repeat one section inside
	  another repeated section), your inner repeated section must use an inner set of markers.
	  For example, you can have a green repeated section inside a blue repeated section, but
	  not the other way around.
	 </p>

	</content>
   </page>

   <page id="drumsdisplay">
	<title>Drums display</title>

	<content>
	 <p>
	  The drums display shows the drum you have selected for each line of the song.
	  It corresponds to the lines shown in the <link id="patterndisplay">pattern
	  display</link>.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  <image file="drumsdisplay.gif" alt="The drums display"/>
	 </p>
   <subhead>Selecting or editing sounds</subhead>
	 <p>
	  To set a drum sound, or to modify an existing sound, click on the name of the
	  sound for that line. This will take you to the <link id="drumscreen">drum
	  screen</link> where you can select a different .wav file and modify
	  the sound.
	 </p>
   <subhead>Adjusting levels</subhead>
	 <p>
	  You can use the level and pan controls to alter the level and left-right
	  positioning of each drum sound. If you click Mute, the drum sound is silenced
    entirely.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  Note that all controls in the drums display refer to those drum sounds
	  throughout the entire song. They are not specific to a particular pattern.
	  If you reduce the level of a hi-hat sound in the drums display, its level
	  will be reduced throughout the entire song, not just in the currently
	  selected pattern. The same applies if you change a sound entirely, or tweak
	  its settings.
	 </p>
   <subhead>Rearranging drums</subhead>
   <p>
     You can rearrange the order of drums (and the corresponding lines in the
     song) by dragging them up and down on this list. This doesn't make any
     difference to the sound, but it could be useful if you want to concentrate
     on particular drums while editing.
   </p>
	</content>
   </page>

   <page id="patterndisplay">
	<title>Pattern display</title>

	<content>
	 <p>
	  The pattern display shows a single pattern of the current song, with
	  the drum hits that have been placed into it. Patterns are always one bar
	  long.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  <image file="patterndisplay.gif" alt="The pattern display"/>
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Pattern selector</subhead>
	 <p>
	  The pattern selector (at the top right) indicates the name of the current
	  pattern. You can change to a different pattern using the left and right
	  arrow buttons.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  It's often quicker to change pattern by right-clicking on the pattern
	  in the <link id="songdisplay">song display</link>.
	 </p>

     <subhead>Control buttons</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Rename</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Click Rename to give the pattern a more descriptive name. This is strongly
	  advised, as it's easy to lose track of patterns when they are only
	  identified with a number.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  When you click Rename, you can type into the pattern name area. You can
	  only type very short names, because the name has to fit in the available
	  space. After you've typed the name, press Enter or click elsewhere to
	  finalise the change.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Duplicate</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Use Duplicate when you want to create a copy of the pattern so that you
	  can modify it slightly.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  The duplicated pattern will have the same name as the original pattern you
	  duplicated, but with a number added at the beginning so that you can
	  distinguish it. For example, if you duplicate a pattern called 'hi-hat',
	  you'll have a copy called '2hi-hat'.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Delete</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Click Delete to remove a pattern from the song. You'll be asked for
	  confirmation: be careful, because deleted patterns cannot be restored.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>New</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Click New to create a new blank pattern. The pattern will be given a number
	  as its name. New patterns are given the same number of beats as the song's
	  initial (bar 1) time signature.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  You can also create blank patterns and place them in the song simultaneously,
	  by Ctrl-left-clicking in the song display.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Main pattern display</subhead>
	 <p>
	  The main part of the pattern display shows a grid on which you can place
	  drum hits.
	 </p>
	 <subsubhead>The pattern grid</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Each horizontal row of the grid corresponds to one drum sound (shown level
	  with the grid in the <link id="drumsdisplay">drums display</link>).
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  The vertical grid lines show where you can place drum hits. If these are
	  not accurate enough, you can turn on 'fine grid' (see below).
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  When you use a time signature with more than four beats per bar, you can
	  use the horizontal scrollbar to reach the beats that are off-screen.
	 </p>
	 <subsubhead>Placing hits</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  When you move
	  the mouse over the grid, you'll see a grey circle appearing over the nearest
	  grid line; this indicates where a hit will be placed if you click.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You place a drum hit by left-clicking on the grid. If there is already a
	  hit in that location, left-clicking there will remove the hit instead.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you want an accented (louder) hit, right-click instead of left-clicking.
	 </p>
	 <subsubhead>Hit display</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Hits are displayed as circles. Normal hits are thin circles; accented hits
	  are thicker circles.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  The display doesn't bear any relation to the actual length of the sound;
	  it only indicates where the sound starts.
	 </p>
	 <subsubhead>Song lines</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  You don't need to manually add more lines to the song; when you use the
	  last line (by placing a hit there), leafDrums will automatically create
	  another line for you to use.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you have more lines than the sixteen that fit on screen, you can use
	  the vertical scrollbar to navigate among them. There is no limit on the
	  number of lines.
	 </p>
	 <subsubhead>Fine grid</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  You can turn on 'fine grid' if you need to place hits more accurately. By
	  default, leafDrums shows beats and quarter beats in the grid; if you turn
	  on 'fine grid', it will also show sixteenth beats.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Once you have turned on 'fine grid', you can place hits on the sixteenth
	  beats. You can turn off fine grid again (the hits won't move or vanish),
	  but if you later want to remove those hits, you will need to turn on
	  'fine grid' once more so that you can click on them.
	 </p>
	 
	 <subhead>Adding and removing beats</subhead>
	 <p>
	  If you change time signature of the song (for example to 3:4) then you need
	  to make sure that patterns match the time signature of the area in which they
	  are used. Placing a pattern with 4 beats in a 3:4 song won't work, and the pattern
	  will be displayed in red as a warning.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can add or remove beats by clicking the 'Remove' or 'Add' buttons at bottom
	  right. Be careful, because when you remove a beat you lose any drum hits from 
	  within that beat.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Triplets</subhead>

   <terminology>
 	  <term>Triplets</term>
	  <definition>
	   <em>Triplets</em> are sections of a rhythm where three hits are placed in the space
	   where two would normally go.
	  </definition>
	 </terminology>

     <subsubhead>Creating triplets</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  If you want to create a triplet, click the 'Triplet' button, then move the mouse over
	  the pattern. The two spaces which will become three are highlighted. When you're in the
	  right place, click the button to make those two grid spaces into three.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  This does not add the actual hits that make up a triplet - it just gives you the
	  appropriately-spaced grid lines so that you can do that yourself.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Triplets only affect a single line of the pattern. If you want them to affect more than
	  one line, repeat the process with each line. There's no limit on the number of triplets
	  in a pattern.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If you begin to place a triplet, but decide you don't want to after all, press the
	  Esc key to cancel.
	 </p>
	 <subsubhead>Removing triplets</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  You can use the same procedure to remove an existing triplet space if you change your
	  mind. (You'll see that the mouseover highlight shows the three grid spaces that will
	  become two.)
	 </p>
	 <subsubhead>Sizes of triplet</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  It is possible to create triplets in three sizes:
	 </p>
	 <ul>
	  <li>Three beats in place of two</li>
	  <li>Three quarter beats in place of two</li>
	  <li>Three sixteenth beats in place of two</li>
	 </ul>
	 <p>
	  The default setting affects quarter beats. If you want to modify
	  entire beats, hold Shift while you click the beats. If you want to modify
	  sixteenth beats, hold Ctrl while you click them.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can have 'triplets within triplets' if you like (by creating
	  a sixteenth-beat triplet inside a quarter-beat triplet, for example).
	 </p>
	</content>
   </page>

  </page>

  <page id="drumscreen">
   <title>Drum screen</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 <image file="drumscreen.gif" alt="Drum screen"/>
	</p>
    <p>
	 This screen contains three sections:
	</p>
	<ul>
	 <li>The <em>control bar</em> (green background)<br/>
	     The control bar is present on this screen as well as on the
		 song screen, so that you can easily play and stop the rhythm
		 while you modify sounds.<br/>
		 <link id="controlbar">More info...</link></li>
	 <li>The <em>sounds display</em> (blue background)<br/>
	     Lists all the sounds that are available to leafDrums, and
		 allows you to select a sound for the current song line.<br/>
		 <link id="soundsdisplay">More info...</link></li>
	 <li>The <em>audio processing display</em> (red-brown background)<br/>
	     Allows you to apply various types of audio processing to the
		 currently-selected sound.<br/>
		 <link id="audiodisplay">More info...</link></li>
	</ul>
   </content>

   <page id="soundsdisplay">
    <title>Sounds display</title>

	<content>
     <p>
	  The sounds display lists all the sounds (.wav and .ogg files) in the folders
	  which leafDrums uses. You can use it to select a sound for the current
	  line of the song.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  <image file="soundsdisplay.gif" alt="Sounds display"/>
	 </p>
	 <subhead>Sound list</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Selecting a sound</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  You can select a sound by clicking on its name. The selected sound has a
	  grey background.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Once you select a sound, this becomes the sound that
	  leafDrums uses for the current line of the song (the line that you
	  clicked on in order to get to the drum screen).
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Files and folders</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  The display lists all the files in folders that leafDrums is using,
	  and in folders within those folders.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Files are listed with their full filename except for the .wav or .ogg.
	  leafDrums only supports .wav and .ogg files, so other file formats aren't
	  shown.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Subfolders are shown with header bars - 'Drums' and 'Cymbals' are
	  the first two examples in the screenshot. The level of indentation
	  indicates which folders are within other folders. In the screenshot,
	  'Drums' is directly within the main leafDrums Sounds folder; 'Cymbals',
	  'Kicks', 'Miscellaneous', 'Snares', and 'Toned' are all folders
	  within the 'Drums' folder.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  You can click on a header bar to hide or show all the files and
	  folders within that folder. This is useful when you have many
	  sound files.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Controls</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Open</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  The Open button (with a folder icon beside it) opens a standard
	  Windows folder window on the main leafDrums folder. You can then drag
	  new files into the folder, or make other changes to the files.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  Note that leafDrums only supports .wav and .ogg files, not any other formats.
	  leafDrums supports any .wav files that your version of Windows can read, and
	  .ogg files that were compressed using Ogg Vorbis. (This means almost any 
	  file with the .ogg extension.)
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  leafDrums is not designed to cope with very large audio files.
	  If a sound is longer than ten bars it will be cut off during
	  playback. If you want to include a very large .wav file in your
	  song (e.g. vocals for an entire track), it's better to keep that
	  file outside leafDrums and mix it with leafDrums's written output
	  later using some other software.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Refresh</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Once you have altered the files in a folder leafDrums is using,
	  you should click Refresh. This updates the list to include any
	  new files you might have added.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Options</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  You can use this button if you want to store drum files in a
	  different location.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  The resulting dialog allows you to add a new folder which leafDrums
	  will use. You can also remove the existing folder if you like (but
	  it is perfectly possible to have files from multiple folders).
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Song</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  Click the Song button to return to the song screen. As a shortcut,
	  you can also press the F5 key.
	 </p>

	</content>
   </page>

   <page id="audiodisplay">
    <title>Audio processing display</title>

	<content>
     <p>
	  The audio processing display lets you apply changes to the sound
	  after leafDrums has loaded it. You can cut parts out of the sound,
	  reverse it, retune it, stretch it to fit the song tempo, and apply various
	  digital effects.
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  <image file="audiodisplay.gif" alt="Audio processing display"/>
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  <em>All</em> changes you might make in the audio processing display affect
	  only the current song; they never alter the original .wav file from
	  which the sound was loaded.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Basic controls</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Test buttons</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  The two Test buttons allow you to check what the sound is like.
	  You can test the original sound, and also the sound that results
	  after all processing has been applied.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  On some computers, you cannot test a sound while the rhythm is
	  playing (you will get an error message). If your computer system
	  is like this, you'll have to stop playing the rhythm before you
	  test sounds.
	 </p>
	 <p class="note">
	  You may not need to use the Test buttons at all; if you place
	  drum hits into the song and leave it playing, you can hear any
	  changes you make right there in the rhythm. (There's a slight
	  delay of about a quarter of a second before changes take effect.)
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Reverse</subsubhead>
   <p>
     If you choose Reverse, the sound will be reversed before any processing
     is applied. (This reversal even applies to the 'Test original' button,
     although of course it does not affect the .wav file on disk.)
   </p>

	 <subsubhead>Accent level control</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  The 'Accent level' slider lets you adjust the level of accented
	  hits on this drum.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  If this slider is in the centre, then accented hits
	  are the same level as normal hits; if it is at the far right,
	  accented hits are twice as loud. By default, accented hits
	  are at 150% of the normal level.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Envelope + trim</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Purpose</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  This section allows you to trim the ends of a sound so that the
	  final sound contains only a portion of the original file. You
	  can also add a fade-out or fade-in.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  The facility is more useful with some sounds than others. In
	  many cases it can be used to alter the attack, length, and
	  decay of drum sounds.
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  For example, by careful manipulation of the length and decay
	  controls, you can make an open hi-hat exactly the right
	  length so that it sounds like it is 'stopped' by a following
	  closed hi-hat hit.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Usage</subsubhead>
	 <p>
	  To enable this section, click the checkbox. (Note that this
	  section cannot be used at the same time as 'Stretch to fit';
	  if that section is currently enabled, it will automatically
	  be disabled.)
	 </p>
	 <p>
	  The four sliders are as follows:
	 </p>
	 <ul>
	  <li><em>Skip</em><br/>
	      Use this slider if you want to skip over some of the
		  beginning of the file and start somewhere in the middle</li>
	  <li><em>Length</em><br/>
	      Adjusts the length of the section used; if you reduce the
		  length, you'll cut off some of the end of the file</li>
	  <li><em>Attack</em> (fade in)<br/>
	      Controls a 'fade in' at the beginning of the sound. The
		  number in milliseconds refers to the length of time it takes
		  to go from zero to full level</li>
	  <li><em>Decay</em> (fade out)<br/>
	      Controls a 'fade out' at the end of the sound. The
		  number in milliseconds refers to the length of time it takes
		  to go from full level to zero</li>
	 </ul>
	 <p class="note">
	  It's possible to overlap the fade in and fade out.
	  (For example, if your sound is 250 milliseconds long, you could
	  have a 200 ms fade in and a 200 ms fade out.) Overlapping the
	  fades doesn't do any harm, but it means the sound will never
	  reach maximum level. You probably don't want to do it.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Tuning</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Purpose</subsubhead>

	 <p>There are three main uses for tuning:</p>

	 <ul>
	  <li>To correct a sound that is slightly out of tune</li>
	  <li>To change the musical pitch of a toned sound</li>
	  <li>To create strange effects</li>
	 </ul>

	 <subsubhead>Usage</subsubhead>

     <p>
	  You can enable tuning by clicking on the checkbox. (Note that this
	  section cannot be used at the same time as 'Stretch to fit';
	  if that section is currently enabled, it will automatically
	  be disabled.)
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  Once enabled, there are four controls:
	 </p>

	 <ul>
	  <li><em>Resample</em> (up/down)<br/>
	      This determines whether you are making the sound higher in
		  pitch (up) or lower (down)</li>
	  <li><em>Octaves</em>, <em>Semi</em><br/>
	      Use these controls to alter the musical pitch of a note
		  by a given number of octaves (up to four) and semitones
		  (up to eleven)</li>
	  <li><em>Fine</em><br/>
	      This control is used for fine-tuning. The number is
		  measured in 1/24th semitones, which should be accurate
		  enough for most purposes</li>
	 </ul>

     <p class="note">
	  As the on-screen text indicates, this facility changes the pitch
	  of your sound by resampling it (equivalent to slowing down or
	  speeding up a record). If you make a sound one octave lower,
	  it also becomes twice as long.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Stretch to fit</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Purpose</subsubhead>

	 <p>
	  This facility allows you to import pre-recorded drum loops into
	  leafDrums, and have them automatically stretched to the correct
	  length (e.g. one bar), even if you change the song's tempo.
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  The drum loops must be recorded and edited precisely, so that
	  the .wav file would sound correct if it were played on continuous
	  loop.
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  You can select smaller parts of these loops after they
	  have been stretched; chopping up loops in this way might help
	  you to create original 'breakbeat' sounds from sampled rhythms.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Usage</subsubhead>

	 <p>
	  To enable this section, click the checkbox. (Note that this
	  section cannot be used at the same time as 'Envelope + trim'
	  or 'tuning'; if those sections are currently enabled, they
	  will automatically be disabled.)
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  There are three sliders:
	 </p>

	 <ul>
	  <li><em>Total length</em><br/>
	      This slider refers to the total length of the drum loop
		  file, in beats. For example, if a 4:4 drum loop is
		  two bars long, you would set this to 8 beats. leafDrums
		  will then stretch the sound so that it is always eight beats
		  long, whatever the tempo</li>
	  <li><em>Skip</em><br/>
	      Use this slider if you want to skip some beats from the
		  start of the loop, so that your sound begins some way
		  into the loop. The slider is measured in beats. (For this
		  to work, you must have set the total length correctly.)</li>
	  <li><em>Output length</em><br/>
	      The companion to Skip, this slider controls the length
		  of the final output sound in terms of beats. You can
		  reduce this slider if you don't want to include some
		  beats at the end of the sound</li>
	 </ul>

     <p class="note">
	  As with tuning, this facility works by resampling the sound.
	  Therefore, stretching the length also affects pitches; if
	  your loop contains toned elements, they'll go out of tune
	  unless your song's tempo is the same that the loop was
	  originally created with.
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Effects</subhead>

	 <subsubhead>Purpose</subsubhead>

     <p>
	  leafDrums contains some simple digital effects which can
	  add interest and richness to your sound. They are also fun
	  if you just want to make weird noises.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Usage</subsubhead>

	 <p>
	  To enable each effect, use the left or right arrows to
	  select the effect type you want.
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  Once enabled, an effect likely won't do anything until
	  you slide the 'effect mix' slider to the right.
	 </p>

   <p>
     The 'time snap' option makes any delay sliders in the effect
     snap to 1/4 beat increments when you drag them, so that you can
     have delays that match the tempo. (If you change the tempo, you'll
     need to come back and edit the delay again.)
   </p>

	 <p>
	  <link id="fx">(Information about specific effects...)</link>
	 </p>

	 <subhead>Presets</subhead>

     <terminology>
 	  <term>Presets</term>
	  <definition>
	   <em>Presets</em>, in leafDrums, are standard disk files which contain
	   all the settings associated with a sound.
	  </definition>
	 </terminology>

	 <p>
	  You can save a sound as a 'preset' and then open it from within another
	  leafDrums song, or from within the same song (if you want another copy
	  of the same sound on a different drum line, for instance).
	 </p>

     <subsubhead>Save</subsubhead>

	 <p>
	  Click this button to save the current sound as a preset. You'll be
	  prompted for a filename.
	 </p>

	 <subsubhead>Open</subsubhead>

	 <p>
	  Click this button to open a preset. The preset overrides settings of
	  the current sound (if they exist).
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  From the open dialog, as well as selecting a file, you can control
	  which aspects of the preset are applied. For example, if you only
	  want to use the same effects, then you can turn off everything
	  except 'Effects'. Effects from the preset file will be applied, but
	  the other settings of your sound will remain the same.
	 </p>

	 <p>
	  Note that if you turn off the 'Sound file' checkbox (so that the file
	  is not changed), you also can't apply 'Envelope and trim' settings.
	  This is because those settings depend on the length of the file, so
	  they can't usefully be applied to a different file.
	 </p>

	 <p class="note">
	  In the Advanced section of this help file, there is a page on
	  <link id="../advanced/presets">using presets creatively</link>.
	 </p>

	</content>

	<page id="fx">
	 <title>Effects</title>

	 <content>
	  <p>
	   leafDrums contains various digital effects. This page explains what
	   the effects do and how to alter their settings to get the result
	   you want.
	  </p>

	  <subsubhead>Effect mix</subsubhead>

	  <p>
	   Most effects contain an 'effect mix' slider. This control alters
	   the balance between the effected sound and the original. If the
	   slider is at the left, you will hear the original sound only;
	   if it's at the right, you will hear the effect result only.
	  </p>

	  <subhead>Delay</subhead>

	  <p>
	   This effect allows you to delay a sound. Normally, you balance
	   the effect mix so that the original undelayed sound can still be
	   heard, giving an echo effect. You can delay each channel (left
	   and right) by different amounts, to result in a stereo delay.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Delay L</em>: time delay applied to the left channel</li>
	   <li><em>Delay R</em>: time delay applied to the right channel</li>
	   <li><em>Feedback</em>: allows you to feed back the delay's output
		   into the input, resulting in multiple echoes</li>
	   <li><em>Delay type</em>: a 'crossed' delay takes its input from
		   the other channel, so that sounds in the left channel will
		   be echoed in the right channel, and vice versa</li>
	   <li><em>Phase</em>: allows you to alter the phase of the delayed
		   output (generally not very useful)</li>
	   <li><em>Feedback phase</em>: altering the phase of the feedback can
		   result in a slightly different sound</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Chorus</subhead>

	  <p>
	   The chorus effect varies the pitch of the original sound up and
	   down slightly as time goes by, creating a version of the sound
	   that's detuned by some amount. Mixing this with the original can
	   create a thicker sound.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Pre-delay L</em>: a time delay on the left channel before
		   the chorus effect is applied</li>
	   <li><em>Pre-delay R</em>: a time delay on the right channel before
		   the chorus affect is applied</li>
 	   <li><em>Depth</em>: the amount by which pitch is varied</li>
 	   <li><em>Speed</em>: the speed at which pitch changes</li>
 	   <li><em>Chorus type</em>: in a stereo chorus effect, the pitch
		   change is opposite in each channel (i.e. when the left channel
		   is higher-pitched, the right channel will be lower-pitched)</li>
 	   <li><em>Waveform</em>: the manner in which pitch varies, either
		   a sine wave or triangle wave. Gives a slightly different sound</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Flanger</subhead>

	  <p>
	   Varies the sound in interesting ways over time. If you set feedback
	   to zero, this is identical to chorus, so put some feedback in.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Pre-delay</em>: amount to delay sound before the flanger
		   effect is applied</li>
	   <li><em>Feedback</em>: how much of its own output the
		   flanger works on compared to the input sound</li>
	   <li><em>Depth</em>: size of pitch change</li>
	   <li><em>Speed</em>: how fast the sound varies (generally sounds
		   better if this is set quite slow)</li>
	   <li><em>Flanger type</em>: like the chorus, a stereo flanger is
		   at the opposite point of its cycle in each channel</li>
	   <li><em>Waveform</em>: sine or triangle wave for the pitch
		   variation</li>
	   <li><em>Feedback type</em>: if you phase-invert the feedback,
		   the effect is usually more noticeable</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Phaser</subhead>

	  <p>
	   The phaser sounds a bit like the flanger, but
	   is more distinctive and produces a pitching effect. (It works by
	   varying the frequency of four filters, but that probably
	   doesn't help explain anything.)
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Depth</em>: amount of variation</li>
	   <li><em>Speed</em>: how fast the sound changes</li>
	   <li><em>Feedback</em>: how much of its own output the
		   phaser works on compared to the input sound</li>
	   <li><em>Base freq.</em>: the base frequency affected
		   (set this higher for a higher-pitched effect)</li>
	   <li><em>Phaser type</em>: a stereo phaser is at the opposite
		   point of its cycle in each channel</li>
	   <li><em>Feedback type</em>: if you phase-invert the feedback,
		   the effect sounds different</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Tremolo</subhead>

	  <p>
	   This effect makes sound volume vary up and down, giving a
	   'wobbly' effect. If you set it to stereo, the sound will
	   seem to move back and forth between the two speakers.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	   It's best to set effect mix all the way to the right with
	   this effect; you can control the amount of effect using
	   the depth slider instead.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Depth</em>: how much the volume changes</li>
	   <li><em>Speed</em>: how fast the sound changes</li>
	   <li><em>Tremolo</em>: a stereo tremolo makes the sound
		   sway from side to side, a mono tremolo makes the volume wobble</li>
 	   <li><em>Waveform</em>: the manner in which volume varies, either
		   a sine wave or triangle wave. Makes little difference</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Distortion</subhead>

	  <p>
	   This is a digital distortion effect. It simply amplifies
	   the sound. If the sound exceeds the maximum level available,
	   it will 'clip' and become distorted.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	   Because this type of distortion makes the sound louder, you
	   can reduce the volume afterwards with the 'Quieten' slider.
	   (If for some reason you only want to reduce sound level and
	   not distort it at all, you can do that too.)
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Distort</em>: the amount by which volume is increased</li>
	   <li><em>Quieten</em>: the amount by which volume should be reduced
		   after applying the distortion</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>EQ</subhead>

	  <p>
  	   EQ allows you to balance the frequencies of the sound. It works in
	   the same way as the "tone" dial on a radio. There is also a
	   "centre frequency" which you can adjust to whatever you think the
	   "normal frequency" is in your sound.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	   You can use either mono or stereo EQ. If you use mono EQ, then the
	   right-channel settings are ignored and left-channel settings are
	   used for both channels, so you don't have to manipulate both
	   sliders.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>L. Centre</em>: centre frequency for left channel</li>
	   <li><em>L. Tone</em>: balances the tone on either side of the centre</li>
	   <li><em>R. Centre</em>: centre frequency for right channel</li>
	   <li><em>R. Tone</em>: balances the tone on either side of the centre</li>
	   <li><em>Channels</em>: if set to mono, the 'L' controls are used
		   for both channels</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Filter (low/high)</subhead>

	  <p>
	   You can use this filter to remove some of the frequencies from the sound.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	   A "low-pass" filter is one in which bass sounds get through, but high-pitched
	   sounds like cymbals are reduced in volume. A high-pass filter is the reverse.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	   If you want to control the amount by which frequencies are reduced, use
	   the effect mix slider.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>L Freq.</em>: frequency below/above which to remove sounds on
		   left channel, or on both channels in a mono filter</li>
	   <li><em>R Freq.</em>: frequency below/above which to remove sounds on
		   right channel; ignored in a mono filter</li>
	   <li><em>Channels</em>: if set to mono, the 'L' controls are used
		   for both channels</li>
	   <li><em>Filter type</em>: a low-pass filter reduces sounds above the
		   selected frequency, and a high-pass filter reduces sounds below
		   the selected frequency</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Filter (band pass)</subhead>

	  <p>
	   This filter lets through sounds that are higher-frequency than the
	   minimum frequency, but lower than the maximum frequency (within a
	   'band').
	  </p>

	  <p>
	   Because the filters aren't too great, the cut-off is not very sharp
	   and there is a "blurred area" around the frequency given; sound is
	   gradually reduced as it gets past the cut-off frequency, not sharply
	   cut. So even if you specify minimum and maximum frequencies to be equal,
	   some sound will still get through.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Min freq.</em>: frequency below which sounds are reduced</li>
	   <li><em>Max freq.</em>: frequency above which sounds are reduced</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Gate</subhead>

	  <p>
	   The 'gate' is an effect that allows sound through only if it is above
	   a certain level.
	  </p>
	  <p>
	   Originally this was used to reduce noise in the pauses between speech
	   or music, but it can also be used as a special effect.
	  </p>
	  <p>
	   The gate 'opens' (allows sound through) when it receives sound above
	   the <em>open level</em>. It closes again when the sound level has gone
	   below the <em>close level</em>. You can control the speed of opening
	   and closing, so that it fades in or out gradually rather than starting
	   or stopping abruptly.
	  </p>
	  <p>
	   Normally you would set effect mix to maximum for a gate effect.
	  </p>

	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Open level</em>: once sound reaches this level, the gate
		   opens to allow it through</li>
	   <li><em>Close level</em>: when the gate is open and sound drops
		   below this level, the gate will close</li>
	   <li><em>In speed</em>: how fast the gate opens</li>
	   <li><em>Out speed</em>: how fast the gate closes</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Compressor</subhead>

	  <p>
	   The compressor is used to reduce sound if it gets above a certain level.
	  </p>
	  <p>
	   The amount by which sound is reduced depends on how far above the given
	   level it is, until sound reaches the <em>upper level</em>, at which point
	   it is always reduced by the full amount.
	  </p>
	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Lower level</em>: when sound reaches this level, it will begin to
		   be reduced</li>
	   <li><em>Upper level</em>: once sound reaches this level, it will be reduced
		   by the maximum amount</li>
	   <li><em>Vol. at max</em>: the volume level which will be applied at maximum
		   (if this is set to zero, the sound will be entirely cut at maximum)</li>
	   <li><em>Fade speed</em>: how fast the compressor reacts to changes</li>
	  </ul>

	  <subhead>Expander</subhead>

	  <p>
	   The expander is similar to the compressor, but works to increase the level
	   of quiet sounds instead of reducing the level of loud sounds.
	  </p>
	  <ul>
	   <li><em>Lower level</em>: when sound drops below this level, it will be increased
		   by the maximum amount</li>
	   <li><em>Upper level</em>: once sound drops past this level, it will be begin to
		   be increased</li>
	   <li><em>Vol. at low</em>: the volume level which will be applied at maximum
		   (there is quite a wide range on this level control, so you can cause
		   distortion if you set it too high)</li>
	   <li><em>Fade speed</em>: how fast the expander reacts to changes</li>
	  </ul>

  	 </content>
    </page>

   </page>
  </page>

  <page id="keyboard">
   <title>Keyboard shortcuts</title>

   <content>
    <p>
     leafDrums has the following keyboard shortcuts:
  	</p>
    <ul>
     <li><em>F5</em> - Jump to song screen</li>
     <li><em>F6</em> - Jump to drum screen (for sound you were editing most
       recently)</li>
     <li><em>F7</em> - If on drum screen, does the same thing as the original
       sound Test button</li>
     <li><em>F8</em> - If on drum screen, does the same thing as the final
       sound Test button</li>
     <li><em>F9</em> or <em>Space</em> - Play or stop playing the song</li>
     <li><em>Ctrl+S</em> - Save the song under the same name it had previously</li>
     <li><em>Esc</em> - Cancel a mode (e.g. if you click Paste then decide you
       don't want to paste anything)</li>
    </ul>
   </content>
  </page>

 </section>

 <section id="advanced" showdepth="1">

  <title>Advanced topics</title>
  <summary>
   These topics are of most interest to people who have already mastered the
   program and are working at creating real drum tracks.
  </summary>

  <content>
   <p>
    The advanced section is kind of a grab-bag of things I wanted to say that
	didn't fit anywhere else. These are suggestions and descriptions of things
	that might be useful if you're getting into the program and using it a
	bit more intensively.
   </p>
  </content>

  <page id="presets">
   <title>Using sound presets creatively</title>
   <content>
    <p>
	 Sound presets are a pretty cool feature. They have two main uses:
	</p>

	<ul>
	 <li>Allowing you to share sounds between different leafDrums songs</li>
	 <li>Helping you to create similar sounds within a song</li>
	</ul>

	<p>
	 In the latter use, you would generally load a preset and then modify
	 it slightly, or load only certain parts of the preset.
	 The two basic techniques are:
	</p>

	<ul>

	 <li>Use the same audio settings for multiple sounds (for consistency)</li>

	 <li>Create several variations of the same sound (for example, applying
	     different depths of an effect), which you can then use to obtain
		 analogue-style effects in which the sound gradually changes
		 through a pattern</li>

	</ul>

   </content>
  </page>

  <page id="simpleloops">
   <title>Using leafDrums with another sequencer</title>
   <content>
    <p>
	 The original version of leafDrums was intended to work with other sequencer
	 program which can play (and loop) .wav files. You can still use this
	 version to do exactly that.
	</p>
	<p>
	 Generally, you will use leafDrums to create a few patterns (perhaps two
	 or four bars at a time), then use the
	 <link id="../reference/controlbar">Write button</link> to save the
	 loop to a .wav file. You can then import the .wav file into your sequencer.
	</p>
	<p>
	 Often you will want to create several variations of the same basic
	 rhythm and save them as different .wav files.
	</p>
	<p>
	 You can do this by putting all the variations in the song and setting
	 the L and R markers to select just one variation. Write this variation
	 to a .wav, then move the markers and repeat for each variation you
	 want to save.
	</p>
   </content>
  </page>

  <page id="wholetracks">

   <title>Creating tracks in leafDrums alone</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 If you are creating certain kinds of music, you may be able to create
	 the entire track (or large portions of a track) in leafDrums, without
	 having to use other sequencer software.
	</p>
	<p>
	 This is good if you are trying to get by without buying expensive
	 software, or if you don't require all the complicated features of
	 such software.
	</p>
	<p>
	 However, leafDrums was primarily designed for drum rhythms, so some
	 things are less than ideal.
	</p>

	<subhead>Basic procedure</subhead>
	<p>
	 Making your track in leafDrums involves recording lots of samples
	 (using your favourite sound recording program) and then putting
	 them together in leafDrums.
	</p>
	<p>
	 For example, you might sample a bass line (either one that you played
	 on some instrument and recorded live, or sequenced in another program
	 and recorded from that), melodies, and so on.
	</p>

	<subhead>Tips</subhead>
	<ul>
	 <li>Decide on a tempo for the song before you record anything<br/>
	     Once you record material to a .wav file, you can't change its tempo
		 without also affecting the pitch</li>
	 <li>If recording live, use a simple drum track or click track<br/>
	     You can use leafDrums to create a click track or simple drum track
		 (e.g. hi-hats) which you can use when you are recording a live
		 performance to make sure that you stay in time</li>
	 <li>Create a new folder for each track<br/>
	     If you put all the sound files for a track in one folder inside
		 the leafDrums Sounds folder, it's easy to keep the materials for
		 the track separate from your normal drums</li>
	 <li>Use 'stretch' to avoid timing differences<br/>
	     In case there are minute timing differences between leafDrums (which
		 times based on your computer's soundcard) and other software that
		 you might use to program melodies for recording, you can use
		 'stretch to fit' (in the <link id="../reference/audiodisplay">audio
		 processing display</link>). This avoids unpleasant tiny gaps, and
		 provided the difference is very small, should not alter pitch too
		 much</li>
	</ul>

	<subhead>Limitations</subhead>
	<ul>
	 <li>leafDrums doesn't do MIDI output<br/>
	     If you prefer to work with MIDI, you'll need to use
		 another program to program melodies or bass lines, and then record
		 the results to a .wav file for leafDrums. (I use my leafLoops,
		 which is a very very simple MIDI sequencer I wrote; it is good
		 enough for creating short melodic sequences)</li>
	 <li>Very large .wav files are not handled particularly well<br/>
	     To begin with, there is an absolute limit of ten bars as the
		 maximum length of any drum hit. In addition, leafDrums stores
		 all sounds in memory, using between two and six times the
		 actual size of the .wav file (see the <link id="performance"
		 >performance</link> section). So you may need to use another
		 program to mix in very long sounds (e.g. vocals for entire
		 track) at the end</li>
	</ul>
   </content>

  </page>

  <page id="performance">
   <title>Software performance issues</title>
   <content>
    <p>
	 leafDrums is a fairly efficient piece of software; key sound mixing code
	 is written in assembly language, for example. You shouldn't have
	 to worry about software performance unless you really push the limits,
	 or you have a very old computer. leafDrums should probably run perfectly
	 well even on 200 MHz PC with 32 MB RAM, for instance.
	</p>

	<p>
	  However, for those few people who need it, I provide this information.
	</p>

	<subhead>How to tell if performance is a problem</subhead>
	<p>
	 Performance is a problem if sound breaks up during playback. If
	 leafDrums can't keep up with the rhythm, there will be gaps in
	 the output sound.
	</p>
	<p>
	 If you have Windows 2000 or XP, you can use the Task Manager (press
	 Ctrl+Alt+Del and click the Task Manager button) to monitor the
	 amount of CPU time and memory that leafDrums is using.
	</p>
	<p>
	 Other programs which you are running at the same time might also
	 be using CPU time or memory which leafDrums could benefit from,
	 so closing down any large programs you are running may improve
	 the situation.
	</p>
	<p>
	 It is possible that other factors, such as soundcard problems,
	 might cause sound break-up. If you get sound break-up even when
	 playing a very simple rhythm (for example, a 4:4 bass beat) then
	 performance is not the problem and something else is wrong.
	</p>

	<subhead>CPU performance issues</subhead>
	<p>
	 CPU time is required during playback primarily to mix sounds.
	 If leafDrums is stuttering during playback, but you don't hear
	 the hard disk thrashing, then CPU time may be the limiting factor.
	</p>
	<subsubhead>Major CPU performance factors</subsubhead>
	<p>
	 CPU time requirements depend on two things:
	</p>
	<ul>
	 <li>The number of drum sounds playing at once</li>
	 <li>Whether you've used level envelopes</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
	 CPU requirement increases directly with the number of drum
	 sounds playing at once (if there are four sounds playing at once,
	 this will use roughly twice as much CPU as if two were playing
	 at once).
	</p>
	<p>
	 Level envelopes are not coded as efficiently as they might
	 be, and the assembly language routine for mixing sounds when
	 the level changes during the sound is slower.
	 Removing a level envelope (by deleting all its nodes) will
	 reduce the CPU requirement slightly.
	</p>

	<subsubhead>Minor CPU performance factors</subsubhead>
	<p>
	 These are likely to make a miniscule difference, and probably
	 no difference at all unless the numbers are really silly.
	</p>
	<ul>
	 <li>The number of tracks in the song with active patterns</li>
	 <li>Very long .wav files</li>
	</ul>

	<subsubhead><em>Non</em>-issues</subsubhead>
	<p>
	 Certain factors do not make a difference to CPU time requirements
	 when you might expect them to.
	</p>
	<p>
	 Primarily, this refers to the <link id="../reference/audiodisplay">audio
	 processing display</link>. All audio processing, including effects,
	 is calculated only when you change settings. Audio processing is
	 not calculated during playback, so it makes no difference to the CPU
	 time requirement.
	</p>

	<subhead>Memory issues</subhead>
	<p>
	 leafDrums works entirely from memory (it does not play sounds
	 from the hard disk). This means that memory could be an issue if you
	 use large sounds or many sounds.
	</p>
	<p>
	 If you hear the hard disk thrashing while leafDrums is playing back,
	 then lack of memory is the most likely cause for your performance
	 problems. (Windows has to store the extra data that should be in
	 memory on disk if it won't fit.)
	</p>

	<subsubhead>Memory consumption</subsubhead>

	<p>
	 Audio data for the sounds in your song is the key factor in
	 memory consumption. Everything else (such as the number of patterns,
	 the number of tracks, and so on) makes only a tiny difference.
	</p>

	<subsubhead>Fixed memory consumption</subsubhead>

    <p>
	 There is a certain base requirement that leafDrums needs just to run.
	 leafDrums uses about 12 MB. Your operating system probably requires
	 at least 16 MB for itself, more if it's a modern version.
	</p>

	<p>
	 So, if you subtract around 28 MB from the total amount of memory in
	 your computer, you have an estimate of the amount of memory you can use
	 for audio data.
	</p>

	<subsubhead>Audio data size</subsubhead>

    <p>
	 As a rough guideline, the memory required for a sound is about three
	 times the size of the .wav file (if it's stereo) or about six times
	 the size (if it's mono). Compressed .ogg files are uncompressed before
	 use, so you don't save memory by using compressed files.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	 This size increases if your song contains tempo changes and the sound
	 is stretched to fit tempo.
	</p>

	<p>
	 If you apply no audio processing at all to the sound, then only
	 about twice the stereo .wav file or four times the mono .wav file
	 will be used.
	</p>

	<p>
	 If your audio processing ends up making the sound longer than it
	 originally was (for example, tuning or stretching that reduces
	 the pitch, or effects which add delay) then more memory will be
	 needed.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	 If you use the same sound file twice e.g. with different effects,
	 it still takes twice as much memory. You don't save memory by
	 reusing the same sound.
	</p>

    <p>
	 What this generally means is that you don't have to worry about
	 small files like drums, which are often less than 100 KB. You
	 might need to worry if you use many very large samples. (For
	 example, a sound that is four bars long at 120 bpm would use
	 around 8 MB of memory; if you only have 32 MB, even one such
	 sound might cause problems. Hopefully you don't have many sounds
	 that are four bars long.)
	</p>

	<subhead>A workaround</subhead>
	<p>
	 If you can't solve your performance problem, a last resort is
	 to write your song to a .wav file. You can then play the .wav
	 file, which shouldn't break up.
	</p>

   </content>
  </page>


 </section>

 <section id="program" showdepth="1">
  <title>About the program</title>

  <content>
   <p>
    The information in this section doesn't directly help you use the
	program; it covers related topics that aren't really 'help'.
   </p>
  </content>

  <page id="ordering">
   <title>Ordering a registered copy</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 You may order a registered (paid-for) copy of leafDrums 2.3 online
	 with a credit card, or by post.
	</p>

	<p>
	 At time of writing, the program only costs <em>30 US dollars</em>.
	 The latest price is displayed on the online ordering website.
	</p>

	<subhead>What you get when you order</subhead>
	<p>
	 leafDrums is already fully functional so that you can properly
	 evaluate it. Therefore, when you register, the program won't do
	 anything more. You will simply receive a key code (and instructions
	 on how to use it) that removes the nag screens and puts your name
	 on the title bar instead of 'unregistered trial version'. Normally
	 this is sent by email.
	</p>

	<p>
	 By making the program fully functional before you register, I'm
	 demonstrating a certain degree of trust; please don't abuse that
	 trust. Register the program if you intend to use it after the trial
	 period.
	</p>

    <p>
	 A registration covers this release and all future 2.x releases (if
	 any). If there is a 3.0 release, there may be a charge.
	</p>

    <subhead>Ordering online</subhead>
	<p>
	 Ordering by credit card is easy and safe. I use an ordering service
	 (Kagi) who will take your credit card details on their secure site. They
	 consider security as a major priority.
	</p>
	<p>
	 If you don't want to use a credit card, Kagi can also accept cheques
	 and money orders in most currencies. On the second page of Kagi's ordering
	 process, you can choose how to pay.
	</p>
	<p>
	 To order online, <link url="http://www.leafdigital.com/software/leafdrums/order.html">click
	 here</link> and follow the instructions.
	</p>
	<p>
	 If you pay by credit card, registration keys are sent automatically,
	 so you should receive your key almost immediately.
	</p>

	<subhead>Site licenses, exemptions, and other information</subhead>

	<subsubhead>Contact me</subsubhead>
    <p>
	 If you want to purchase a site license for leafDrums, or you have
	 other special requirements, please email me:
	 <link url="http://www.leafdigital.com/contact/?leafdrums">leafDrums@leafdigital.com</link>
	</p>
	<p>	 
	 In particular, a number of UK schools are using leafDrums in their teaching.
	 If you work at a state school in the UK and would like to use leafDrums in your
	 teaching, I have arranged a special standard discount programme which I'm certain 
	 your school can afford. Please contact me for details. 
	</p>
	<p>
	 Discounts are also available for other educational institutions (universities,
	 schools in other countries, etc.) on a case-by-case basis.
	</p>

	<subsubhead>Exemptions</subsubhead>

	<p>
	 If you really, truly cannot afford to register leafDrums (and I mean
	 genuinely cannot afford; if you go out and buy music CDs or other
	 similar luxuries, then you can afford this software) then please
	 feel free to use it without paying.
	</p>

    <p>
	 This doesn't apply if you are a child unless your parents are similarly
	 poor; you probably bug them to buy you other things, please bug them
	 to buy you leafDrums as well. It certainly doesn't apply to institutions
	 or companies.
	</p>

	<p>
	 I won't send anyone a free registration code, so don't bother to contact me,
	 but if you are genuinely short of money, don't feel that you are obligated
	 to register.
	</p>

   </content>

  </page>

  <page id="changes">
   <title>Changes from older versions</title>
   <content>
   <subhead>Changes between 2.24 and 2.3</subhead>
   <p>
    Significant update. Please note that once you save a file with 2.3, it cannot be
    loaded in earlier versions.
   </p>
   <ul>
    <li>You can now change tempo and time signature within a song.</li>
    <li>leafDrums now uses a standard Windows window and can be resized or maximised as desired.</li>
    <li>Autosave feature stores a copy of your work every 5 minutes. If leafDrums crashes (or you kill it or turn your PC off), then the last autosaved version will be automatically loaded next time you run leafDrums.</li>
    <li>Now supports all standard .wav file formats (including compressed formats) for loading drum sounds.</li>
    <li>Also supports Ogg Vorbis format files for drum sounds...</li>
    <li>...and for the Write feature. (This is useful when you want to put a copy of your song on a webpage for people to download.) </li>
   </ul>
   <subhead>Changes between 2.23 and 2.24</subhead>
   <p>
     Update with fixes to all other reported bugs. Please note that 
		 files saved with 2.24 cannot be loaded in earlier versions.
   </p>
   <ul>
	   <li>Bugfix: re-opening the same file now reverts 
		   to the saved version instead of doing nothing</li>
		 <li>Bugfix: if you save the file with a different
		   name, it now remembers this the next time you save
			 (instead of offering the previous name as default)</li>
		 <li>Bugfix: if you rearrange the order of drum lines
		   by dragging, this order is now saved</li>
		 <li>Bugfix: inserting or deleting bars didn't move the 
		   repeat arrows correctly; they moved on-screen but did
			 not immediately update on playback</li>
		 <li>Bugfix: writing as separate tracks didn't work</li>
		 <li>UI fix: when writing as separate tracks, track numbers
		   now start from 1 instead of 0</li>
		 <li>Bugfix: when writing out tracks, it now doesn't write
		   a file for tracks that are entirely blank</li>
		 <li>Bugfix: select and paste was still broken, I think it's
		   fixed now</li>
		 <li>Help file updated, version number and copyright date changed</li> 
   </ul>
   <subhead>Changes between 2.22 and 2.23</subhead>
   <p>
     Another minor bugfix.
   </p>
   <ul>
	   <li>Bugfix: clicking below the last drum name (on the song screen)
		   caused crash</li>
   </ul>
   <subhead>Changes between 2.21 and 2.22</subhead>
   <p>
     An embarrassing-mistake update.
   </p>
   <ul>
	   <li>Bugfix: opening song files didn't work</li>
   </ul>
   <subhead>Changes between 2.2 and 2.21</subhead>
   <p>
     A bugfix update.
   </p>
   <ul>
	   <li>Bugfix: scrolling the drum list caused crash</li>
		 <li>Bugfix: select/paste caused crash</li>
		 <li>UI fix: if you click Open and select a .wav or something it
       tells you that doesn't work and you should do it with the drum screen</li>
		 <li>UI fix: changed text slightly in Write dialog</li>
   </ul>
   <subhead>Changes between 2.11 and 2.2</subhead>
   <p>
     This update includes several new features, a few user interface improvements,
     and some bugfixes.
   </p>
   <ul>
     <li><em>Select and paste</em> in song</li>
     <li>Ability to <em>write multiple .wav files</em> for use with multitrack
       software</li>
     <li><em>Mute</em> facility for individual drum sounds</li>
     <li>Ability to <em>rearrange drum lines</em> to the order you prefer</li>
     <li>Drum sounds can be <em>reversed</em></li>
     <li>Can <em>synch delay times to tempo</em> in effects (Time Snap)</li>
     <li>UI fix: keyboard shortcuts (F7, F8) to test sounds in audio screen</li>
     <li>UI fix: changing tempo is now less slow (when you hold down the right button
       to increase tempo, it accelerates)</li>
     <li>UI fix: double-clicking a drum name in the song screen no longer causes
       something to happen in the audio screen</li>
     <li>UI fix: the Loop button now directly controls playback looping (it was
       just too confusing before)</li>
     <li>UI fix: the song now begins with a single pattern placed in it; previously
       people were confused by having to place the pattern in the song</li>
     <li>UI fix: now uses the song name as a default name for the Write .wav file</li>
     <li>Bugfix: markers and flags now shift along when you insert
       or delete bars</li>
     <li>Bugfix: no longer crashes if you duplicate a pattern, then delete the
       original</li>
     <li>Bugfix: sometimes used to give an error about not being able to play the test
       sound, even though it just played it; this is now fixed</li>
     <li>Version number updated to 2.2 everywhere</li>
     <li>Help file updated for new version and improved slightly</li>
   </ul>

    <subhead>Changes between 2.1 and 2.11</subhead>
	<ul>
	 <li><em>Duplicate</em> button now works again</li>
    </ul>

    <subhead>Changes between 2.0 and 2.1</subhead>
	<p>
	 This minor update fixes several bugs and also includes some new features
	 that people asked for.
	</p>
	<subsubhead>Bug fixes</subsubhead>
	<ul>
	 <li><em>Tempo</em> is now set correctly when you load a song</li>
	 <li><em>Test buttons</em> in the audio screen now work correctly</li>
	 <li>A crash bug when <em>creating triplets</em> is fixed</li>
	 <li>Another crash bug when <em>playing back triplets</em> immediately
	     after you created them is also fixed</li>
	 <li>If you <em>double-click to open a file</em>, this no longer
	     causes an on-screen button to be pressed as well</li>
    </ul>

	<subsubhead>New features</subsubhead>
	<ul>
	 <li><em>Flags and arrows</em> allow you to repeat sections of the song</li>
	 <li><em>Insert</em> and <em>Delete</em> buttons allow you to add or remove bars in
	     the song without having to re-enter all the patterns</li>
	 <li>The song grid now <em>scrolls with playback</em></li>
	 <li>Bars in the song grid are <em>numbered</em> so you can see where you are</li>
	 <li>You can now use the <em>space bar</em> instead of clicking Play/Stop</li>
	 <li>Pressing <em>Escape</em> cancels temporary modes (triplet placement,
	     insert/delete bar)</li>
	 <li>The Escape key functionality is shown on screen</li>
	 <li>This help file has been updated to include the new features</li>
	</ul>

    <subhead>Changes between 1.04 and 2.0</subhead>
    <p>
	 Most of the program was rewritten for this version. All the changes were
	 based on user feedback over the years; if you're one of those who sent
	 email to me about the software, thank you, and I hope some of the
	 things you asked for have now been addressed.
	</p>

	<p>
	 (I'm pretty hyped about this update - I honestly believe it's now a
	 really top-class program. If you've been using the old version, I hope
	 you're as excited by the improvements.)
	</p>

    <p>
	 In any case, here are the key changes:
	</p>
	<ul>
	 <li><em>Different file format</em> - leafDrums 2 cannot read the old
	     file format because the internal structures were all changed to make
		 the system more flexible. The new format has been designed to support
		 future enhancements, so hopefully this won't happen again. If you
		 still need to use leafDrums rhythms, you can have the old leafDrums
		 installed on your computer at the same time without problems</li>
	 <li><em>DirectSound playback</em> - Using DirectX improves playback
	     performance and makes leafDrums co-operate better with other
		 programs. leafDrums should work with any version of DirectX, but
		 if you have problems, install DirectX 8</li>
	 <li><em>Song support</em> - many people were using leafDrums to create
	     drum rhythms throughout entire songs, a task for which it wasn't
		 suitable. This version includes song support so that you can have
		 many copies of a pattern without losing the ability to make changes
		 to it</li>
	 <li><em>More flexible timing</em> - leafDrums 2 supports triplets and
	     different time signatures, two frequently requested features</li>
	 <li><em>Better composition</em> - you can play two patterns at the
	     same time, which means you can separate out component elements of
		 the rhythm into separate patterns and avoid having to repeat them</li>
	 <li><em>Level fades</em> - the lack of support for fading sounds in and
	     out in the old version really bugged me; now you can do it via the
		 'Level envelope' feature</li>
	 <li><em>Better file selection</em> - the list of .wav files to select
	     from is now much larger and hierarchical so that you can realistically
		 use a large selection of drums</li>
	 <li><em>No distinction between drums and loops</em> - loops are used
	     with the 'stretch to fit' option instead, which simplifies the
		 interface</li>
	 <li><em>Redesigned user interface</em> - while the intentions behind the
	     old interface (to have everything available on-screen rather than
		 hidden in menus, to support quick, convenient use) were good, the
		 interface was not always clear and the visual design made it difficult
		 to see. The new interface has been designed for maximum clarity and
		 to provide much more visual help in using the software</li>
	 <li><em>Same design principles</em> - like the first version, leafDrums 2
	     is intended to be easy to use, quick to use, and powerful, allowing
		 you to get started immediately and create interesting sounds</li>
    </ul>
   </content>
  </page>

  <page id="credits">
   <title>Credits</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 All code, graphics, and documentation by <em>Samuel Marshall</em>/leafdigital.
	 Copyright &#x00a9; 2005 Samuel Marshall. All rights reserved.
	</p>

	<p>
	 sam would like to thank:
	</p>

	<ul>
	 <li><em>Targaff</em> - testing<br/>
	     Targaff kindly tested this version for me (despite that I hadn't
		 written the help file by then) and found at least one critical
		 bug which I wouldn't otherwise have noticed. He also pointed out a few
		 areas which needed improvement before release.</li>
     <li><em>David Gosnell</em> - drum sounds<br/>
	     David sampled the drum sounds which are installed with leafDrums
		 in this and the previous version.</li>
     <li><em>Wizzu</em> - mailing list<br/>
	     Wizzu generously agreed to host the <link id="community">mailing
		 list</link> for me.</li>
	 <li><em>Chris Hurley</em> - forum<br/>
	     Chris volunteered to host the <link id="community">Web forum</link>.</li>
	 <li><em>All those who made suggestions</em><br/>
	     I do appreciate all suggestions for the program and try to reply
		 to all your emails, although of course I can't implement
		 everything.</li>
    </ul>

   </content>

  </page>

  <page id="contact">
   <title>Contacting the author</title>

   <content>
    <p>
	 You can contact me by email via my website, which also contains a current
	 FAQ list:
	</p>

	<p>
	 <link url="http://www.leafdigital.com/contact/?leafdrums">Contact page</link>
	</p>

	<p>
	 If you want to ask questions about the program, make suggestions, report
	 a bug etc., you can do that to the above address, but in many cases it
	 might be better to post to the <link id="community">mailing list or Web forum</link>
	 instead.
	</p>

  <p>
    Please do make sure you have read the relevant sections in the help file
    and have <em>gone through the tutorial</em> before you contact me to ask
    a question. I get a lot of questions that are covered in the tutorial.
  </p>

   </content>

  </page>

  <page id="community">
   <title>leafDrums community</title>

   <content>
    <p>
     A mailing list and a Web forum for discussing leafDrums are both available.
     Please feel free to use these if you have problems with the software or have 
     anything else you would like to share with other users.
    </p>
    <p>
	 See the <link url="http://www.leafdigital.com/software/leafdrums/community.html">Community 
	 page of the leafDrums website</link> for current details about both facilities.
	</p>

   </content>

  </page>
 </section>

</help>

